#### Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/davidspeights (LinkedIn) appriss.com (Other)

#### Top Skills

Predictive Modeling SAS Statistical Modeling

#### **Publications**

Criminological Theory and Loss Prevention

Return Rate Miscalculations Impact More Than 50% Of Companies Nationwide

Retail Theft and Loss Prevention Analytics

Experimental Design and Loss Prevention Programs

Big Data

# David Speights, PhD

Chief Data Scientist, Appriss

Tustin, California

# Summary

Experienced analytics professional with hands on data and modeling experience using the latest tools. Over 15 years of experience managing statisticians, data scientists, and data analysts and working with data and statistical models for Retail, Insurance, Banking, criminal justice, opioid risk,Pharmaceutical, and Direct marketing. Over 15 years of programming experience with SAS, SQL, and experienced with a variety of formal programming languages and scripting languages like python, c, and c++. I personally have built or supervised the construction of models which are at work in many Fortune 500 companies. Have presented analytics solutions to "C" level executives and leaders (including the governor of Michigan) or senior managers at over 100 companies and have given presentations at conferences more than 40 times and taught several analytics seminars.

Specialties: Predictive modeling, machine learning, handling large complex data sets, SAS and its interaction with netezza and hadoop, return fraud detection, direct mail fundraising models, text mining, targetted marketing, data mining, analytics, SAS programming, SAS automation, SAS reporting, measuring ROI of predictive models, presenting analytics solutions to executive level management, data management, survival analysis, workers compensation loss reserving, mortgage modeling, risk modeling, data cleaning, data manipulation, hadoop, hive, impala.

## Experience

Appriss
Chief Data Scientist
December 2016 - Present (3 years 4 months)

Manage team of 19 responsible for Modeling, Analytics, and Data management for Appriss' Retail, Public Safety and Healthcare business units. Primary support for Sales, Operations, Finance, and Business Development

on internal and external analytics and strategic partnerships and discussions. Frequently make presentations to C-level executives at commercial customers and government agencies at current and prospective clients.

The Retail Equation
Chief Data Scientist
March 2004 - November 2016 (12 years 9 months)
Irvine, CA

Member of the senior management team and direct report to the CEO. Developed from scratch all analytics, machine learning, data processing and predictive modeling based intellectual property. With the company since just after the founding until its sale (two times) to a private equity firm and a strategic buyer (Appriss). Grew analytics team from 1 to 14 members supporting more than 30 retailers

### Washington Mutual

First Vice President, Credit Modeling and Analytics August 2001 - February 2004 (2 years 7 months)

Managed team responsible for designing and building risk models for underwriting new mortgages and managing Washington Mutual's \$100 Billion residential mortgage portfolio.

HNC Software
Chief Statistician

March 1997 - August 2001 (4 years 6 months)

Managed team responsible for modeling and analytics for MIRA and Vericomp Subro. MIRA is a claim level loss reserving software system that is used at several of the largest insurance companies in the country.

## Education

University of California, Los Angeles Ph.D., M.S., Biostatistics · (1993 - 1997)

California State Polytechnic University-Pomona BS, Mathematics (with emphasis on Statistics) · (1989 - 1993)